window.__examLoadCallback({
  "title": "Computer_Organization - Computer_Organization — Slot 9 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Computer_Organization — Slot 9",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>Assume that 16-bit CPU is trying to access a double word stating at an odd address. How many memory operations are required to access the data? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2014)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>1</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>2</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>3</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>4</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>3</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/52438/isro2014-40\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Suppose you want to build a memory with 4 byte words and a capacity of \\(2^{21}\\) bits. What is type of decoder required if the memory is built using \\(2K \\times 8\\) RAM chips? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2014)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>5 to 32</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>6 to 64</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>4 to 16</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>7 to 128</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>5 to 32</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/15028/isro2014-25\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>If each address space represents one byte of storage space, how many address lines are needed to access RAM chips arranged in a \\(4 \\times 6\\) array, where each chip is \\(8K \\times 4\\) bits ? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2014)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>13</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>15</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>16</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>17</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>17</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/15027/isro2014-17\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>The memory access time is 1 nanosecond for a read operation with a hit in cache, 5\nnanoseconds for a read operation with a miss in cache, 2 nanoseconds for a write operation\nwith a hit in cache and 10 nanoseconds for a write operation with a miss in cache. Execution\nof a sequence of instructions involves 100 instruction fetch operations, 60 memory operand\nread operations and 40 memory operand write operations. The cache hit-ratio is 0.9. The\naverage memory access time (in nanoseconds) in executing the sequence of instructions is\n__________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "1.68",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2078/gate2014-3-44#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>An instruction pipeline has five stages, namely, instruction fetch (IF), instruction decode and register fetch (ID/RF), instruction execution (Ex), memory access (MEM), and register write back (WB) with stage latencies 1 ns, 2.2 ns, 2 ns, 1 ns, and 0.75 ns, respectively (ns stands for nanoseconds). To gain in terms of frequency, the designers have decided to split the ID/RF stage into three stages (ID, RF1, RF2) each of latency 2.2/3 ns. Also, the Ex stage is split into two stages (Ex1, Ex2) each of latency 1 ns. The new design has a total of eight pipeline stages. A program has 20% branch instructions which execute in the Ex stage and produce the next instruction pointer at the end of the Ex stage in the old design and at the end of the Ex2 stage in the new design. The IF stage stalls after fetching a branch instruction until the next instruction pointer is computed. All instructions other than the branch instruction have an average CPI of one in both the designs. The execution times of this program on the old and the new design are P and Q nanoseconds, respectively. The value of P/Q is __________ <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "1.5",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2077/gate2014-3-43#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following processors (ns stands for nanoseconds).\nAssume that the pipeline registers have zero latency. <br>\nP1:  Four-stage pipeline with stage latencies 1 ns, 2 ns, 2 ns, 1 ns. <br>\nP2:  Four-stage pipeline with stage latencies 1 ns, 1.5 ns, 1.5 ns, 1.5 ns. <br>\nP3:  Five-stage pipeline with stage latencies 0.5 ns, 1 ns, 1 ns, 0.6 ns, 1 ns. <br>\nP4:  Five-stage pipeline with stage latencies 0.5 ns, 0.5 ns, 1 ns, 1 ns, 1.1 ns. <br>\nWhich processor has the highest peak clock frequency? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>P1</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>P2</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>P3</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>P4</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>P3</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2043/gate2014-3-9#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>Consider a main memory system that consists of 8 memory modules attached to the system\nbus, which is one word wide. When a write request is made, the bus is occupied for 100\nnanoseconds (ns) by the data, address, and control signals. During the same 100 ns, and for\n500 ns thereafter, the addressed memory module executes one cycle accepting and storing the data. The (internal) operation of different memory modules may overlap in time, but only one request can be on the bus at any time. The maximum number of stores (of one word each) that can be initiated in 1 millisecond is ____________ <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "10000",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2022/gate2014-2-55#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>If the associativity of a processor cache is doubled while keeping the capacity and block size\nunchanged, which one of the following is guaranteed to be NOT affected? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Width of tag comparator</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Width of set index decoder</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Width of way selection multiplexor</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Width of processor to main memory data bus</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>Width of processor to main memory data bus</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2010/gate2014-2-44#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>In designing a computer's cache system, the cache block (or cache line) size is an important\nParameter. Which one of the following statements is correct in this context? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>A smaller block size implies better spatial locality</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>A smaller block size implies a smaller cache tag and hence lower cache tag overhead</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>A smaller block size implies a larger cache tag and hence lower cache hit time</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>A smaller block size incurs a lower cache miss penalty</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>A smaller block size incurs a lower cache miss penalty</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2009/gate2014-2-43#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>A 4-way set-associative cache memory unit with a capacity of 16 KB is built using a block\nsize of 8 words. The word length is 32 bits. The size of the physical address space is 4 GB.\nThe number of bits for the TAG field is _____ <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "20",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1963/gate2014-2-9#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>Consider two processors P1 and P2 executing the same instruction set. Assume that under\nidentical conditions, for the same input, a program running on P2 takes 25% less time but\nincurs 20% more CPI (clock cycles per instruction) as compared to the program running on\nP1. If the clock frequency of P1 is 1GHz, then the clock frequency of P2 (in GHz) is _________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "1.6",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1935/gate2014-1-55#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>An access sequence of cache block addresses is of length N and contains n unique block\naddresses. The number of unique block addresses between two consecutive accesses to the\nsame block address is bounded above K. What is the miss ratio if the access sequence is\npassed through a cache of associativity A\\(\\geq\\)k exercising least-recently-used replacement policy? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>n/N</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>1/N</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>1/A</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>k/n</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>n/N</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1922/gate2014-1-44#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>Consider a 6-stage instruction pipeline, where all stages are perfectly balanced. Assume that\nthere is no cycle-time overhead of pipelining. When an application is executing on this 6-stage pipeline, the speedup achieved with respect to non-pipelined execution if 25% of the instructions incur 2 pipeline stall cycles is _________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "4",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1921/gate2014-1-43#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>A machine has a 32-bit architecture, with 1-word long instructions. It has 64 registers, each of  which is 32 bits long. It needs to support 45 instructions, which have an immediate operand in addition to two register operands. Assuming that the immediate operand is an unsigned integer, the maximum value of the immediate operand is ____________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "16383",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1767/gate2014-1-9#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>In case of a DVD, the speed of data transfer is mentioned in multiples of? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2013)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>150 KB/s</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>1.38 MB/s</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>300 KB/s</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>2.40 MB/s</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>1.38 MB/s</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/44397/isro-2013-51\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
});
